hey what's up guys my name is a China
welcome back to my c++ series so today
we're gonna be talking all about timing
so how do we time how long it takes for
us to complete a certain operation or
execute certain code that is what
today's we are going to be about now
timing is useful for so many things
whether or not you want something to
happen at a certain time or if you're
just kind of evaluating your performance
or benchmarking and seeing how fast your
code runs you need to know how much time
passes while you up while your
application is actually running there
are several ways to achieve this since
C++ 11 we have something called Chronos
essentially say it's essentially part of
the library that is becomes with C++ and
it's not something that we actually have
to go to the operating system library to
actually do before if you wanted a high
resolution time on meaning you wanted a
very very precise timer you need to
actually use the operating systems
library so in Windows for example we
have something called query performance
counter we can still use that stuff and
in fact if you want a little bit more
control of how you actually access that
timing capability of your CPU then you
probably do want to use the platform
specific libraries however today we're
just going to be taking a look at the
kind of platform-independent c++
standard library way of figuring out how
long or how much time passes between our
lines of code as they get executed and
that is part of the chrono library now
I've linked a link in the description
below to the actual cpp reference for
this chrono kind of API I'm going to
show you a very simple way of how we can
set it up and start using it here so
that we can figure out how long it takes
us to run certain code and I'll probably
also show you one way in which it can be
useful now this whole video is going to
be important for the future of this
series because as we start integrating
more kind of complex features and I
start talking more and more about how to
do things properly and how to write good
performing code we're going to be using
timing to see that difference so if I
show you a kind of slow way of doing
things and then I say well actually it
would be better if we did it this way
you'll be able to actually see the
difference in terms of how long it takes
to
actually run that code so this is very
important from this will probably branch
into benchmarking and I'll talk more
about benchmarking in another video and
we can set up some kind of API so that
we can time how long it takes to
complete functions and arbitrary scopes
code probably as well so yeah pay
attention to this video let's jump right
into it and learn how we can time a
curve so the first thing I'm going to do
here is include Krona this contains
pretty much everything we need I'm also
going to include thread because we'll do
some stuff with that in a minute as well
so from chrono it's very very simple to
actually use that library and figure out
what the current time is we can just
type in STD chrono high resolution clock
and then now this is what actually gives
us the current time if you hover over
this you can see it returns a time point
of SUV current sit o'clock it's quite a
long type which is why I'm just going to
use order and kind of label this as the
starting time we're then going to
execute some kind of code here what I'm
going to do for now because I don't
actually have any other code to execute
of the week and time I'm just going to
write sed this thread sleep for and then
we'll just write 1s for one second and
to get that will actually have to use a
namespace STD literals and chrono
literals to get that s there okay cool
so basically what we're doing now is
we're telling this thread this current
thread to sleep for one second so we're
saying just kind of pauses pause
execution for one second so obviously by
writing this code when we have our start
and our end timing we should see it be
around one second probably won't be
exactly one second because first of all
thread sleeps are not guaranteed to be
exactly how much you tell it to sleep
for but also they'll be overhead from
the actual timing so if we get back into
this I'll right order end and this will
be exactly the same as this start code
here and finally we want to figure out
the actual duration so I'll write SVD
chrono duration well we can just get
this in floats that'll be high enough
resolution for us I'll call this
duration and it will just be end minus
start just like that we could have used
order here as well but this type isn't
quite as long so it's fine to write down
and finally I'm just going to see out
that into the console direction don't
count and
and this will be in seconds I'll just
add s to the end of that so that's clear
if I hit f5 you can see the number we
get here is pretty much around one
second so that's it what I just showed
you is a platform-independent way of
actually figuring out how long something
takes or how much time passes or getting
the current time and all that this
kernel library is fantastic it's very
high resolution timing and it works on
pretty much all platforms so really I
recommend that you use this for all of
your timing needs unless you're
specifically doing some kind of
low-level things so you want to reduce
overhead even more if you're running a
huge game engine or some kind of cool
library you might want to use the
platform independent I'm sorry the
platform specific library such as the
win32 api with the query performance
counter and stuff we might look into
that in the future but really there's
pretty much no need for 99% of cases
just use STD kroehner now if we dive
back into this I'm going to show you a
bit of a smarter way of actually dealing
with this because you can see that this
is quite a lot of code that we have to
run so support suppose that we have a
function I'll call it function and it
does something like maybe just prints
out in our hello to the console a bunch
of times so I'll just wrap this in a for
loop and I'll say maybe it does that
about a hundred times or something like
that
right so we have a for loop it runs a
hundred times we want to figure out well
how long is this see out operation
really how long does it take C out to
actually write stuff out to the console
a hundred times I want to time this
function so what I could do at this
point is copy start and end and do all
of that stuff that's a lot of work I
don't really want to do that instead I'm
actually going to set up a very very
basic struct or class doesn't matter
just make this a struct called timer and
this will actually do everything for me
and what I'm going to do here is I'm
going to use the whole object lifetime
kind of paradigm to actually get it to
basically automatically time everything
for me if you guys haven't checked out
the video on object lifetime and C++
definitely do that it's very very useful
and in fact this example I'm pretty sure
I did actually give in that video as
well and so jumping back into our code
the constructor is going to actually
start the timer so I'm going to grab
this and put it in here unfortunately I
actually use order so I'm gonna have to
figure out what the type is which is sed
Pro note time point s any corner City
cloth so
TV chrono time point s TV chrono steady
clock so that's how kind of start just
call this start and put it up here so we
have our start and our end and I also
grabbed this from here a direction and
put this in that's the duration start
I'm going to assign to this in the
constructor and in the destructor when I
copy this whole code here in the in the
destructor what I'm actually going to do
is write and equals the same thing and
then finally curation and I mean you
don't really have to store and as you
can see because we're really just up at
the duration but in case people want to
access that maybe I want to kind of
write that into my timer struct so
generation equals and minus dot and that
will give us the direction in seconds of
course okay and that's really all I need
let's just make it even easier and say
that we actually print the duration so
we'll say time I took and then I'll
write in duration seconds now because
this is such a quick operation we
actually might want to print the
milliseconds instead so I will say flirt
M s equals duration of count times 1,000
which will give us the value in
milliseconds and I'll change this to be
m/s and this to be MS okay cool sounds
pretty good to me that's pretty much all
I need here and now we have a basic
structure that will basically do the
timing and even print it up for us
automatically and it will of course do
that upon destruction all we really need
to do is just create the object at the
beginning of our function and that's
that's it so over here in my function
the way I'm going to do this is just
type in time a time up like that that's
all I have to do and I'm done
this entire scope this entire function
will now be timed so if I go back and
delete all of this crap that I that I
don't care about I'm just going to call
function like that and we'll hit f5 and
say what happens okay cool so check this
out we get pelo printing a hundred times
to the console and at the very end we
say that this took 122 milliseconds cool
so we now know how long our part
actually takes 122 milliseconds very
very slow let's see if we might be able
to optimize
a little bit so a CDN line seems to be
quite slower for some reason so if we
just get rid of that and actually put a
backslash n into our print here inside
our function let's see how much faster
this will be and you can see over here
that we've caught out about a third of
our execution time obviously you should
run this a few more times and in release
mode if you actually care about
benchmarking and all of that but for now
we can still see the difference anyway
that is a basic overview of timing in
C++ and how you can time your functions
and see how long it takes to execute
certain code obviously this was a very
very rough example I was just showing
you how to actually use that timing API
not how to actually perform benchmarks
we're going to have a video all about
that in the future you can of course
also use visual studios profiling tools
or whatever idea you're using whatever
tool say you're using a lot of tools do
have profiling tools built in so you can
actually automate a lot of this this is
more or less something called
instrumentation where you actually
modify your source code to contain kind
of profiling tools such as this timing
that can be very very useful because not
all platforms you work with are going to
have good enough profile of the dart and
overhead and this is a really simple way
to do it there are so many things that
you can actually do from this you can
basically collect the data into like one
big file and output it and read it in
another tool so that you can see graphs
or even like kind of a diagram of how
long each function takes and what
function that function calls and there's
so many things that will extend from
this that we'll explore in the future so
definitely get excited about that very
important that you start doing this if
you do care about performance since I
imagine a lot of people watching this
series are game developers or people who
want to write game engines you need to
be doing stuff like this all the time to
actually see how fast your probe
performs and since you are using C++ as
a language you're using C++ probably
because you care about performance and
you want to write fast code so
definitely get used to this kind of
stuff anyway I hope you guys enjoyed
this video if you did you can hit the
like button you can also help support
this series by going over to patreon
look on 4/2 churner huge thank you as
always to all of my patrons this series
would not be here without you I can kind
of cent guarantee that so they
he's so much and I will see you guys in
the next video goodbye
[Music]